Kristin M. Eccles

Curriculum Vitae

Website: https://kristineccles.wordpress.com

Contact Information Division of the National Toxicology Program

National Institute of Environmental Health Sciences

530 Davis Dr. Keystone Building Durham, NC 27713

GitHub: https://github.com/kristineccles

E-mail: kristin.eccles@nih.gov

Voice: (919) 998-9954

ORCID: 0000-0002-6629-430X

Highlights

19 journal publications (10 as first author) 260 citations; h index = 9 and i10 index = 9

Research interests: Exposome, biomarkers, NAMs, geospatial modeling, spatial epidemiology

CURRENT POSITION Postdoctoral Research Fellow

Nov 2020 - Present

National Institute of Environmental Health Science, Division of the National Toxicology Program,

Durham, North Carolina, USA

Postdoctoral Advisors: Cynthia Rider, Ph.D and Kyle Messier, Ph.D.

EDUCATION

Ph.D., Biology with Specialization in Chemical and Environmental Toxicology 2019

Department of Biology, University of Ottawa, Ottawa, Canada

Dissertation Advisor: Laurie Chan, Ph.D.

M.Sc., Geography

2014

Department of Geography, University of Calgary, Calgary, Canada Advisors: Stefania Bertazzon, Ph.D. and Sylvia Checkley, Ph.D.

Honours B.A., Major: Health Studies, Minors: Geography and Earth Science 2012

McMaster University, Hamilton, Canada

Advisor: John Eyles, Ph.D.

Professional APPOINTMENT/ EMPLOYMENT

Postdoctoral Fellowship

Aug 2019 - Oct 2020

Department of Geography, Geomatics and Environment, University of Toronto, Mississauga, Canada Postdoctoral Advisors: Igor Lehnherr, Ph.D. and Trevor Porter, Ph.D.

Geomatics Researcher

June 2017 - March 2019

National Wildlife Researcher Center, Environment and Climate Change Canada, Ottawa, Canada

Research Assistant

Sept 2014 - Dec 2019

First Nation Food Nutrition and Environment Study, University of Ottawa, Ottawa, Canada

Peer-reviewed **Publications**

Eccles K.M., Karmaus A.L., Parham, F., Rider, C.V., Kleinstreuer, N.C., Wambaugh, J.F., Messier, K.P. (In Press). A geospatial modeling approach to quantifying risk of exposure to environmental chemical mixtures via a common molecular target. Science of the Total Environment.

Cui, Y., Eccles K.M., Kwok, R.K., Joubert, B., Messier, K.P., Balshaw, D. (2022). Integrating Multiscale Geospatial Environmental Data into Large Population Health Studies: Challenges and Opportunities. Toxics. 10(403). https://doi.org/10.3390/toxics1007040

- Thomas, P. J., Eickmeyer, D. C., **Eccles, K.M.**, Kimpe, L. E., Felzel, E., Brouwer, A., Blais, J. M. (2022). Paleotoxicity of petrogenic and pyrogenic hydrocarbon mixtures in sediment cores from the Athabasca oil sands region, Alberta (Canada). *Environmental Pollution*, 118271. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envpol.2021.118271
- Eccles, K.M., Thomas, P. J., Chan, H. M. (2021). Spatial patterns of the exposure-response relationship between mercury and cortisol in the fur of river otter (*Lontra canadensis*). *Chemosphere*, 263, 127992. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemosphere.2020.127992
- Thomas, P. J., Newell, E. E., **Eccles, K.M.**, Holloway, A. C., Idowu, I., Xia, Z., Quenneville, C. (2021). Co-exposures to trace elements and polycyclic aromatic compounds (PACs) impacts North American river otter (*Lontra canadensis*) baculum. *Chemosphere*, 265, 128920. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemosphere.2020.128920
- **Eccles, K.M.**, Pauli, B.D., Chan, H.M. (2020). Geospatial analysis of complex metal exposures to biota in the Athabasca Oil Sands. *PLoS one*, 15(9), e0239086. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0239086
- Galen, G., Eccles, K.M., MacMillian, M., Thomas, P. J., Chan, H.M., Poulain, A.J. (2020). The gut microbial community structure of the North American river otter (*Lontra canadensis*) in the Alberta Oil Sands Region in Canada: relationship with local environmental variables and metal body burden. *Environmental toxicology and chemistry*. 39(12), 2516-2526. https://doi.org/10.1002/etc.4876
- Etowa, J., Johnston, A., Jama, Z., **Eccles, K.M.**, Ashton, A. (2020). Mixed-method evaluation of a community-based postpartum support program: a study protocol. *BMJ open*, 10(10), e036749. https://doi.org/10.1136/bmjopen-2019-036749
- Eccles, K.M., Majeed, H., Lehnherr, I., Porter, T. (2020). A continental and marine-influenced tree-ring mercury record in the Old Crow Flats, Yukon, Canada. *ACS Earth and Space Chemistry*, 4(8), 1281-1290. https://doi.org/10.1021/acsearthspacechem.0c00081.s001
- Cheney, C.L., **Eccles, K.M.**, Kimpe, L.E., Blais, J.M. (2020). Determining the effects of past gold mining using a sediment palaeotoxicity model. *Science of The Total Environment*, 718, 137308. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2020.137308
- Eccles, K.M., Thomas, P. J., Chan, H. M. (2020). Relationships between mercury concentrations in fur and stomach contents of river otter (*Lontra canadensis*) and mink (*Neovison vison*) in northern Alberta Canada and their applications as proxies for environmental factors determining mercury bioavailability. *Environmental Research*, 181, 108961. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envres.2019.108961
- Eccles, K. M., Pauli, B. D., Chan, H. M. (2019). The use of Geographic Information Systems (GIS) for spatial ecological risk assessments: An example from the Athabasca oil sands area in Canada. *Environmental toxicology and chemistry*, 38(12): 27972810. https://doi.org/10.1002/etc.4577
- Eccles, K. M., Littlewood, E. S., Thomas, P. J., Chan, H. M. (2019). Distribution of organic and inorganic mercury across the pelts of Canadian river otter (*Lontra canadensis*). *Scientific reports*, 9(1), 3237. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-019-39893-w
- Eccles, K. M., Thomas, P. J., Chan, H. M. (2017). Predictive meta-regressions relating mercury-tissue concentrations of freshwater piscivorous mammals. *Environmental Toxicology and Chemistry*, 36(6), 23772384. http://doi.org/10.1002/etc.3775
- Thomas, P. J., Eccles, K. M., Mundy, L. J. (2017). Spatial modelling of non-target exposure to anticoagulant rodenticides can inform mitigation options in two boreal predators inhabiting areas

with intensive oil and gas development. *Biological Conservation*, 212, 111-119. https://doi.org/10.1002/etc.3775

Hu, X. F., Eccles, K. M., Chan, H. M. (2017). High selenium exposure lowers the odds ratios for hypertension, stroke, and myocardial infarction associated with mercury exposure among Inuit in Canada. *Environment International*, 102, 200-206. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envint.2017.03.002

Eccles, K. M., Checkley, S., Sjogren, D., Barkema, H. W., Bertazzon, S. (2017). Lessons learned from the 2013 Calgary flood: Assessing risk of drinking water well contamination. *Applied Geography*, 80, 78-85. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.apgeog.2017.02.005

Eccles, K.M., Bertazzon, S. (2015). Applications of geographic information systems in public health: A geospatial approach to analyzing MMR immunization uptake in Alberta. *Canadian Journal of Public Health*, 106(6). https://doi.org/10.17269/cjph.106.4981

Bertazzon, S., Johnson, M., **Eccles, K.**, Kaplan, G. G. (2015). Accounting for spatial effects in land use regression for urban air pollution modelling. *Spatial and Spatio-temporal Epidemiology*. 14-15, 921. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.sste.2015.06.002

Manuscripts in Progress

Lowe, M.E., Akhtari, F., Potter, P.A., Fargo, D.C., Schmitt, C.P., Schurman, S.H., **Eccles, K.M.**, Motsinger-Reif, A., Hall, J.E., Messier, K.P.The skin is no barrier to mixtures: Air pollutant mixtures and reported psoriasis or eczema in the Personalized Environment and Genes Study (PEGS). (In Revisions)

Boutet, V., Dominique, M., **Eccles, K.M.**, Branigan, M., Dyck, M., van Coeverden de Groot, P., Lougheed, S.C., Rutter A., Langlois V.S. A spatial contaminant assessment for polar bear (Ursus maritimus) liver, fat, and muscle from Northern Canada. (In Revisions)

Schock, D.M., Akhter, F., Mundy, L., **Eccles K.M.**, Soos, C., Papp, Z., Pauli., B. Spatial and temporal variation of metal concentrations in wetlands and wood frogs from the Athabasca oil sands region in northern Alberta, Canada. (In Peer Review)

Tommasi, F., Pagano, G., Oral, R., Thomas, P.J., **Eccles K.M.**, Tez, S., Toscanesi, M., Giarra,, A., Siciliano, A., Dipierro, N., Gjata, I., Guida, M., Libralato, G., Lyons, D.M., Buri, P., Ines Kovai, I., Trifuoggi, M. Topsoil pollution and multi-endpoint toxicity in the petrochemical area of Augusta-Priolo (eastern Sicily, Italy). (In Peer Review)

Conference Proceedings

Eccles K.M., Thomas P.J., Chan H.M. (2016). Evaluating mercury guidelines for furbearers using a predictive meta-model. Canadian Ecotoxicity Workshop. Edmonton, Canada.

Bertazzon, S., Barrett, O., Johnson, M., Eccles, K, Zhang, J. Y. (2014). Land use regression models (LUR) for reliable estimation of air quality in Calgary. Spatial Knowledge and Information. Banff, Canada.

INVITED TALKS

Eccles K.M. (2020). From biomarkers to biomes: Relationships between contaminant sources, exposures, and health outcomes. University of Toronto Intersectional Seminar Series. Toronto, Ontario.

Eccles K.M. (2020). Humans, wildlife, and the environment: Assessing ecological health. 2nd Annual GeoHealth Network Conference. Toronto, Ontario. (Not presented due to COVID-19)

Eccles K.M., Chan H.M. (2018). Mercury in wild foods and food security: Integrating data (Presentation). Environment and Climate Change Canada (ECCC) Wildlife Division Health Division Annual Meeting. Ottawa, Ontario.

Eccles K.M., Chan H.M. (2018). Modelling the relationship between contaminant sources and exposures in wildlife (Presentation). Environment and Climate Change Canada (ECCC) National Pollution Release Inventory (NPRI) Data Users Workshop. Ottawa, Ontario.

SELECTED CONFERENCE PRESENTATIONS

Eccles K.M., Messier, K.P., (2021). Geospatial Risk Characterization Mapping of Chemical Mixtures Through Connections to Toxicological Adverse Outcome Pathways (Presentation). American Geophysical Union, New Orlean, USA.

Eccles K.M., Kleinstreuer, N.C., Wambaugh, J.F., Messier, K.P., (2021). A geospatial modeling approach to quantifying risk of exposure to environmental chemical mixtures via a common molecular initiating event (Poster). International Society of Environmental Epidemiology, New York, USA.

Eccles K.M., Clackett A., Ghotra, A., Majeed, I., Lehnherr, I., Porter, T. (2020). Developing a network of historical atmospheric mercury trends using tree-rings in northern Canada (Presentation). Society of Environmental Toxicology and Chemistry, Fort Worth, USA.

Eccles K.M., Clackett A., Ghotra, A., Majeed, I., Lehnherr, I., Porter, T. (2019). Assessing variability of atmospheric mercury (Hg⁰) trends using tree-rings in northern Canada (Presentation). Society of Environmental Toxicology and Chemistry. Toronto, Canada.

Eccles K.M., Thomas P.J., Chan H.M. (2019). Wildlife as a surrogate indicator for impacts of mercury on ecosystem health (Presentation). International Conference on Mercury as a Global Pollutant. Krakow, Poland.

Eccles K.M., Thomas P.J., Chan H.M. (2018). Wildlife as a surrogate indicator for impacts of mercury on ecosystem health (Presentation). Society of Environmental Toxicology and Chemistry. Sacramento, USA.

Eccles K.M., Thomas P.J., Chan H.M. (2018). Evaluating the co-dispersion of mercury sources and wildlife exposures in the Athabasca Oil Sands region (Presentation). Society of Environmental Toxicology and Chemistry. Sacramento, USA.

Eccles, K.M, Hebert C.E., Schock, D., Akhter F., Mundy L., Thomas P.J., Pauli, B.D. (2018). Evaluating the co-dispersion of mercury sources and wildlife exposures in the Athabasca Oil Sands region (Presentation). Society of Environmental Toxicology and Chemistry. Sacramento, USA.

Eccles K.M., Thomas P.J., Chan H.M. (2018). Using geospatial methods to quantify the codispersion of mercury sources and exposures in river otter (*Lontra canadensis*) for risk prediction (Presentation). International Society of Exposure Science and International Society of Environmental Epidemiology Joint Meeting. Ottawa, Canada.

Eccles K.M., Pauli, B., Chan H.M. (2017). Using Geographical Information Systems (GIS) for spatial risk assessment and landscape ecotoxicology (Presentation). Canadian Ecotoxicity Workshop. Guelph, Canada.

Eccles K.M., Thomas P.J., Pauli, B., Chan H.M. (2017). Assessing chemical mixture exposures using spatial Principle Components Analysis (sPCA) and Geospatial Methods (Presentation). SETAC Special Meeting: Mixtures. Denver, USA.

Eccles K.M., Thomas P.J., Chan H.M. (2017). Modelling fur as a non-invasive biomarker for environmental mercury exposure (Presentation). International Conference on Mercury as a Global Pollutant. Providence, USA.

Eccles K.M., Thomas P.J., Chan H.M. (2016). Evaluating mercury guidelines for furbearers using a predictive meta-model (Presentation). Canadian Ecotoxicity Workshop. Edmonton, Canada.

Teaching
EXPERIENCE

Primary Instructor

Graduate Level Short Course: Introduction to R in Open-Source Methods

Department of Geography, Geomatics and Environment, University of Toronto

Winter 2020

Geographic Information Systems Spring 2020

Department of Geography, Geomatics and Enviornment, University of Toronto

Introduction to Quantitative Methods Winter 2018

Department of Geography and Environmental Studies, Carleton University

Mapping and Modelling the Real World: Introduction to GIS

May 2017

Enrichment Mini-Course, University of Ottawa

Introduction to Geomatics Fall 2016

Department of Geography, Environment and Geomatics, University of Ottawa

Teaching Assistant

University of Ottawa, Ottawa, ON
Spatial Ecology, Biostatistics, Environmental Science

Spatial Ecology, Diostatistics, Environmental Science

Competitive Awards

University of Toronto Postdoctoral Award (2019-2020)	\$45,000
NSERC CREATE-REACT (2016 - 2018)	\$20,000
NSERC CREATE-REACT Travel Award (2018)	\$5,000
University of Ottawa Excellence Scholarship (2016 - 2017)	\$8,200
Queen Elizabeth II Graduate Scholarship in Science and Technology (2016 - 2017)	\$15,000
University of Ottawa Entrance Scholarship (2014 - 2018)	\$38,000

LEADERSHIP AND SERVICE

Conference Sessions and Workshops Delivered

Society of Environmental Toxicology and Chemistry, Fort Worth, USA

Nov 2020

Sept 2019

On Demand Session: Mercury emissions, transport, and transformation in a changing environment Live Discussion: Pathways between Hg sources and exposures in a changing world

Workshop: Introduction to R

International Conference on Mercury as a Global Pollutant, Krakow, Poland

Workshop: Latest Advances in Wildlife Biomonitoring

Expert Working Group Member

Arctic Monitoring Assessment Program (AMAP)

Mercury Expert Working Group

Oil Sands Monitoring Integration Workshop Series

Jan 2019

June 2019- Sept 2020

External Expert for Geospatial Analysis and Mercury

Training in the Responsible Conduct of Research, National Institutes of Health Fall 2021 Additional Training Teaching Fundamentals Certificate, University of Toronto Winter 2020 Machine Learning, University of Toronto Fall 2019

LANGUAGES English - Native Language, French - Good

R - Advanced, Python - Intermediate, LaTeX- Intermediate

Professional Society of Toxicology (SOT)

Memberships Society of Environmental Chemistry and Toxicology (SETAC)

Data Visualization Society